A Guide to the Warren Chappell Papers, 1870-1994
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Warren Chappell Papers, 1870-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10204-av
ca. 3,300 items (18 Hollinger boxes and seven oversize boxes, ca. 18.5 linear shelf feet)
The collection, 1870-1994, consists chiefly of Warren Chappell's illustrations, artwork, sketches and drawings; personal and professional correspondence; and articles, catalogs and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of American book illustrator and artist, Warren Chappell (1904-1991) consists of ca. 3,300 items, ca. 1870-1994, chiefly Chappell's illustrations and artwork for books, dust jackets, magazines, Book-of-the-Month Club announcements, keepsakes, bookplates, and Christmas card designs; and individual sketches and drawings by Chappell and other artists (including some pre-twentieth century artists), but also including personal and professional correspondence; printed material; some photographs; articles; talks and speeches by Chappell; exhibition catalogs featuring Chappell; reviews and notices for books illustrated or written by Chappell; examples of various typefaces; political cartoons; and various topical files. Also present are some manuscripts and drawings by Chappell's grandfather, John Taylor Chappell (1845-1915), and Samuel Michael Chappell.
Organization
Series I: Topical & Miscellaneous Files
Subseries A: Artwork by Chappell & Other Artists (Boxes 1-2; Oversize Boxes N-1, S-34, S-35)
Subseries B: Topical & Miscellaneous Files (Boxes 3-8; Oversize Boxes N-1, )
Subseries C: Correspondence (Boxes 8-10)
Series II: Artwork & Illustrations by Warren Chappell for Books, arranged by book title (Boxes 11-18; Oversize Boxes S-32, S-33, S-35)
Contents List
- Topical & Miscellaneous Files
  - Artwork by Chappell & Other Artists
    - Artwork, Calendar & Posters concerning "Rudolph Koch and the Offenbach Workshop" 1931-1932, 1980 (Box N-1)
    - Artwork by Isabel Bishop 1982, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Isabel Bishop n.d. (Box S-35)
    - Artwork by Paul Cadmus n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by George Cattermole 1925 (Box S-35)
    - Artwork by [Guy?] Fleming n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Artwork by Willi Harwerth 1932-1934, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Rudolf Koch, including a notice of his death 1927-1934 (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Fritz Kredel n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Fritz Kredel n.d. (Box S-35)
    - Artwork by Allen Lewis 1931, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Charles Locke 1930, n.d. (Box S-35)
    - Artwork by Imre Reiner n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Boardman Robinson 1930-1937, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Boardman Robinson, including 3 political cartoons [1918], 1922-1923 (Box N-1)
    - Artwork by Boardman Robinson 1923-1937 (Box S-35)
    - Artwork by J. Rodin 1978 (Box S-35)
    - Artwork by Rudolph Ruzicka 1935 (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Ernest H. Shepard n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Hugo Steiner 1944 (Box S-35)
    - Artwork - Unidentified 1935, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Artwork by Various Artists, 16th-19 Century: Hieronymus Bang (1553-1630); Annibale Carracci (1560-1609); Sebastiano Conca (1680-1764); [Salomon ?] Koninck (1609-1656); Charles Parrocel (1688- 1752); Giovanni Piazetta (1682-1754); Francesco Solimena (1657-1747); and Unidentified Flemish work (Box S-35)
    - Bookplates Cut & Engraved by Gustav Eichenauer n.d. (Box 1)
    - Bookplates Designed by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 1)
    - Calendars Designed by Warren Chappell 1953-1961 (Box 1)
    - Calligraphic Broadside by Eric Gill concerning Edward Johnston n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Cartoons - Political by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 1)
    - Christmas Card Designs ca. 1938-1959 (Box 1)
    - Christmas Card Designs by Warren Chappell ca. 1930-1985 (Box 1)
    - Christmas Card Designs for the Associates of the University of Virginia Library by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 1)
    - Christmas Card Designs for Alfred and Clarice Hamill by Warren Chappell 1945-1952 (Box 1)
    - Christmas Card Designs by Allen Lewis 1930-1954 (Box 2)
    - Christmas Card Designs by Ernest H. Shepard 1948-1965, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Colored Plates (2) from a botany book, Alopecurus pratensis and Holcus Canatus n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Designs for Emblems, Ornaments & Logotypes 1970, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Designs for End Paper Patterns & Borders 1957, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Drawings & Sketches by John Taylor Chappell and Samuel Michael Chappell ca. 1870-1884, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Drawings & sketches (Pencil) by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 2)
    - Four French Caricatures n.d. (Box S-35)
    - Engravings (facsimiles) n.d. (Box 2)
    - Engraving of [Pieter Breughel?] n.d. (Box S-35)
    - Engraving of Peter Paul Rubens Picture n.d. (Box N-1)
    - German Calligraphic Broadside by [Berthold Wolpe?] 1931 (Box N-1)
    - Gustav Dore's Illustrations for the Biblen.d. (Box S-33)
    - Letterheads n.d. (Box 2)
    - Pen & Ink Drawings "As one oldster to another" and two farm scenes (unidentified) n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Pen & Ink Drawings (2) by John B. Crouchlee, including "Sabines" n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Pen & Ink Drawing by [Walter Jack] Duncan n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Pen & Ink Drawings of Fishermen from Glouchester, Virginia; and Nudes 1932, n.d. (Box S-34)
    - Pen & Ink Drawings - Unidentified n.d. (Box S-34)
    - Pen & Ink Sketches by Warren Chappell 1931, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Pen & Ink Sketches - Nudes by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 2)
    - Pencil Drawing of Prospect Lake n.d. (Box S-34)
    - Prints - Bewick Owls from wood engravings by the English engraver Thomas Bewick (1753-1828) 1975 (Box 2)
    - Print by Hunter Middleton from a Thomas Bewick block of a bird n.d. (Box 2)
    - Printed Poster folded into a binder entitled "The Story of Advertising is the Story of Human Progress illustrated by Joseph Feher" 1944 (Box S-34)
    - Sketches of Warren Chappell [Self-Portraits?] n.d. (Box 2)
    - Ten Political Cartoons by Warren Chappell 1940 & n.d. (Box S-35)
    - "Vow of Moderation in a New Position"by Paul Horgan for Warren Chappell 1969 (Box 2)
    - Woodcuts (2) by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 2)
  - Topical & Miscellaneous Files
    - The Art Students League of New York 1927-1946 (Box 3)
    - Articles 1953 & 1957 (Box 3)
    - Articles by Alfred Fairbank 1963-1974, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Article by Fritz Kredel in Philobiblon, with a letter from Fritz and Annie Dredel to Warren Chappell, 29 April 1973 1971 (Box 3)
    - Articles by Paul Standard 1940, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Articles by Warren Chappell, including: "The Woodcut in Book Decoration," "Illustrations Today in Children's Books," "Artist vs. Craftsman?" "Bench Marks for Illustrations of Children's Books," "Art vs. Adventitious Circumstances," "Let's Make a Bfor Bennett," and "The Anatomy of Printing" 1934-1976 (Box 3)
    - Biographical Information 1932-1951, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Blow-ups of Various Scripts n.d. (Box S-34)
    - Bookbinding Examples, Pictures of n.d. (Box 3)
    - Book-of-the-Month Club 1945-1974 (Box 3)
    - Borzoi Books 1941-1966 (Box 3)
    - Certificates, Posters, and Other Printed Items 1925-1994 (Box S-35)
      Includes: Art Students' League Poster for the Fiftieth Anniversary Exhibition by Allen Lewis; Windrose Zur Landkarte von Deutschland Poster by Warren Chappell and Berthold L. Wolpe; Printed illustration by Fritz Kredel from Soldiers of the American Army 1775-1941; Littera Scripta Manet Posters printed at the Acorn Press; Poster advertising Warren Chappell and The Frederic W. Goudy Distinguished Lecture in Typography For 1970; Poster by Andrew Hoyem "In the Beginning/Was the Word/The Word Was God/In Him Was Life; American Typecasting Fellowship Certificate; Poster advertising "University of San Francisco Symposium XIX Egypt People of the Sun"; Exhibition Poster "Warren Chappell Artist and Artificer in the Twentieth-Century Book World."
    - Chronicles of Culture Tear Sheets 1978-1982 (Box 3)
    - Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center 1935-1936 (Box 3)
    - Counterpunch and Stock for Punch & Counterpunch n.d. (Box 3)
    - "Designs for U.S. Stamps - Opinions by 12 of the Country's Leading Design Authorities" Chappell featured on pages 12-13 n.d. (Box 4)
    - Development Brochure for the Special Collections Department at the University of Virginia n.d. (Box 4)
    - Dinner given by Friends of Warren Chappell1955 (Box 4)
    - Dust Jackets A-Y ca. 1948-1978, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Dust Jacket Artwork ca. 1950-1968 (Box 5)
    - Enigmas Manuscript by Ted [Hodnett] n.d. (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "American Type Designers and Their Type Faces on Exhibit" 1948 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "American Type Designers and Their Work" Lakside Press Galleries R.R. Donnelley & Sons Company, Chicago 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Book Designs and Illustrations of Warren Chappell on Display at at New Canaan, [Connecticut] Library" n.d. (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - Books Designed, Illstrated or Printed in Great Britain for Mr. George Macy of New York, British Museum, London1952 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "A Charles Dickens Christmas: An Exhibition of Drawings by Warren Chappell for A Christmas Carol, The Chimes, and Cricket on the Hearth", University of Virginia, Bayly Museum 1976 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Charles Locke's New York" 1984 Mar-Apr (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Fifty Books of the Year MCMXXXVI" 1936 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Gallery 303 of The Composing Room, Inc. presents Warren Chappell A Retrospective" 1970 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Illustrations for Herman Melville's Moby Dick A Suite of Drawings by Warren Chappell" University of Virginia, Bayly Art Museum 1975 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Lettering and Calligraphy in Current Advertising and Publishing" 1945 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Littera Scripta Manet My Life With Letters" University of Virginia Special Collections 1983 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Pensacola National Calligraphy Exhibition" 1985 (Box 5)
    - Exhibition - "Warren Chappell Artist and Artificer in the Twentieth-Century Book World" 1994 (Box 5)
    - The Horn Book Magazine Cover 1951 & 1979 (Box 5)
    - The Illustrated Modern Library n.d. (Box 5)
    - Interview with George W. Bunn, Jr., Hobby Horse Press, conducted by Sally Bunn Schanbacher 1972 (Box 5)
    - Invitations & Programs for Talks by Warren Chappell 1937-1980 (Box 5)
    - Italix The Warren Chappell Number 1975 (Box 5)
    - Keepsake - The Fugitives, The Agrarians and Other Twentieth-Century Southern Writers1985 (Box 5)
    - Keepsake - The Imprints of Gloomth The Gothic Novel of England1988, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Keepsake - A Salute to Clifton Waller Barrett1981, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Keepsake - Writers in Residence and Resident Writersn.d. (Box 6)
    - Lecture - "Forty-Odd Years in the Black Arts" Goudy Lecture 1970 (Box 6)
    - Lecture - "The Living Alphabet" for Heritage of Graphic Arts Lecture 1975 (Box 6)
    - Lecture - "The Phylogeny of Books" n.d. (Box 6)
    - Leslie, Dr. Robert L. - 100th Birthday and Honor from Typophiles 1973 & 1985 (Box 6)
    - Lunceon honoring Charles Smith 1963 (Box 6)
    - Magazine Covers 1946-1956 (Box 6)
    - Manuscripts of John Taylor Chappell (1845-1915) n.d. (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1967, 1981-1987, n.d. (Box 6)
    - PEN/Faulkner Award Design ca. 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Photograph of Boardman Robinson n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Photographs 1912-1983, n.d. (Box 7)
    - Poems by Robert Barrett n.d. (Box 7)
    - Poem by S[amuel?] W. Chappell Ode To Michelangelo's David1923 (Box 7)
    - Poster for Exhibit "Littera Scripta Manet" n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Printed Material 1922, 1939-1986 (Box 7)
    - Printed Material - Gebr. Klingspor, Offenbach am Main 1927-1985, n.d. (Box 7)
    - Program for Dedication of the Clemons Library 1982 Apr 13 (Box 7)
    - Reader's Digest 1965-1968 (Box 7)
    - Religious Poster I N R I in Latin with a design of Christ crucified in the middle n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Reproduction of Renoir Painting by the Metropolitan Museum of Art n.d. (Box N-1)
    - Reviews & Notices re Books Illustrated/written by Warren Chappell 1936-1984, n.d. (Box 7)
    - Reviews & Notices re A Short History of the Printed Word 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - Robert Frost Medal by Sedgewick n.d. (Box 7)
    - Rockford Papers- Tear Sheets 1980-1982 (Box 7)
    - "Stories from Moliere" by Warren Chappell n.d. (Box 7)
    - Trip to Puerto Rico with "The Junketeers" 1973 (Box 7)
    - Type Showings 1927-1957, n.d. (Box 8)
    - Type Showings - Blow-ups n.d. (Box 8)
    - Type Showings - D. Stempel AG 1984, n.d. (Box 8)
    - Type Showings - Lydian 1938-1941, n.d. (Box 8)
    - Type Showings - Trajanus ca. 1949 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, A-Z 1923-1987, 2 folders (Box 8)
      Including: Amsterdam Continental; Sally Boggan; Matthew J. Bruccoli; Nash Burger; Paul Cadmus; Warren Chappell to Mr. Grabhorn re his stay at Offenbach, 1931 Aug 24 (typed copy); Carroll Coleman; Rick Cusick; George Mason University; Elizabeth Sage Hare; S.L. Hartz; Weston P. Hatfield; Thayer Hobson; Andrew Hoyem; Fridolf Johnson; Herb Johnson; Dorothy Kenyon; Liza Kirwin; Karl Hermann Klingpor; J. Van Krimpen; William McCleery; S.C. Mitchell; Dumas Malone; Mrs. Barrows Mussey; Joseph Pennell; R. Hoe & Co., Inc.; Rudolph Ruzicka; Harry Scherman; Anthony M. Schulte; Max Schuster; Ellery Sedgwicke; Al Silverman; Fred Smith; Paul Standard; [Louis M. Starr]; Francis Steegmuller-Hazzard; Stinehour Press; University of Richmond; Edward Wagenknecht; Robert Penn Warren (postcard); Eva Williams; Stuart Wright; Lili & Erich Wronker; Hermann Zapf; and Unidentified Correspondents
    - Bernard & Barbara Arnest 1986 (Box 9)
    - Arnold Bank 1981-1983 (Box 9)
    - Martin & Ruthe Battestin 1982, n.d. (Box 9)
    - Isabel Bishop 1949, 1979-1984 (Box 9)
    - Guy Botterill The House of Type 1983-1984 (Box 9)
    - D. Stempel AG, Frankfurt Am Main 1939-1983, 1986 (Box 9)
    - Max Dorn 1950-1956 (Box 9)
    - re Dinner given by Friends of Warren Chappell1955 (Box 9)
    - Alfred Fairbanks 1968-1986 (Box 9)
    - Alfred Hamill 1944-1946, 1951 (Box 9)
    - Willi Harwerth 1932-1965 (Box 9)
    - Julius S. Held 1982-1984 (Box 9)
    - Howard M. Jones 1943-1944, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Neal T. Jones 1982-1983 (Box 9)
    - Alfred Knopf 1980-1983 (Box 9)
    - Charles Locke 1970-1976 (Box 9)
    - Ruth Nuzum 1981-1986 (Box 10)
    - Boardman Robinson 1934-1949, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Ernest Howard Shepard, with clippings of Punch Mastheads by Shepard 1946-1965 (Box 10)
    - re A Short History of the Printed Word 1970-1975 (Box 10)
    - University of Virginia 1976-1984 (Box 10)
    - John Updike 1961-1962, 1981-1984 (Box 10)
- Artwork & Illustrations by Chappell for Books
  - ABC Alphabet Book n.d. (Box 11)
  - The Adventure and Travels of Frank Folly n.d. (Box 11)
  - The Adventures of Hanspfaall n.d. (Box 11)
  - All the King's Men 1981, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - All the King's Men 1981, artwork and dust jacket (Box S-33)
  - Alladdin or the Wonderful Lamp, illustrated by C. Hodgson 1831 (Box 11)
  - Anatomy of Letters by Warren Chappell 1976 (Box 11)
  - The American Imagination at Work 1947 (Box 11)
  - Angels & Awakenings 1980, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Angels and Awakenings, They Say Stories, and Comedies and Tragedies of Shakespeare1944, 1980 (Box N-1)
  - Angels and Awakenings, A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court, and The Complete Novels of Jane Austen1950, 1980 (Box S-30)
  - The Borzoi Book of French Folk Tales 1956 (Box 11)
  - Boswell for the Defense 1770-1774 1959 (Box 11)
  - Boswell on the Grand Tour Germany and Switzerland 1953 (Box 11)
  - Bottom's Dream 1968-1969, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Captain Coxcombe and the Pirates of Cathay 1950 (Box 12)
  - A Charles Dickens Christmas 1976 (Box 12)
  - A Charles Dickens Christmas and The Sleeping Beauty1961, 1976 (Box S-31)
  - Comedies and Tragedies of Shakespeare 1944 (Box S-33)
  - Comedies and Tragedies of Shakespeare 1944, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - The Complete Adventures of Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry Finn 1978 (Box 13)
  - The Complete Adventures of Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry Finn 1978 (Box S-32)
  - Complete Novels of Jane Austen 1950 (Box 13)
  - Connecticut Yankee n.d. (Box 13)
  - The Divine Order Western Culture in the Middle Ages and the Renaissance 1969 (Box 13)
  - Doctor Dogbody's Leg 1940 (Box 13)
  - Don Quixote de La Mancha 1960, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - The Fairy Ring 1967 (Box 13)
  - The Fisherman and His Wife n.d. (Box 13)
  - The Food of Italy 1971 (Box 13)
  - Frog Went a-Courtin' A Woman's Day Chapbook 1953 (Box 13)
  - French Fairy Tales 1968 (Box 13)
  - Gulliver's Travels 1977 (Box 13)
  - Gulliver's Travels & A Voyage to Laputa 1976-1977 (Box S-32)
  - Home is the Sailor 1964 (Box 13)
  - The Lay of the Love and Death of Cornet Christoph Rilke 1983, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - The Light in the Forest 1966 (Box 14)
  - The Little Book of the Ballet n.d. (Box 14)
  - The Magic Flute 1962, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - The Magic Flute, Pennybold, and Don Quixote1939, 1962, n.d. (Box S-31)
  - The Mermaid ca. 1973 (Box 15)
  - Miracle at Philadelphia 1986 (Box 15)
  - Mr. Midshipman Easy 1956 (Box 15)
  - Mozart [1956?] (Box 15)
  - Mrs. Searwood's Secret Weapon 1954 (Box 15)
  - The Nutcracker 1958, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Nutcracker 1958, 1980 (Box S-33)
  - The Parables from the Old and New Testaments n.d. (Box 15)
  - The Party of Humanity Essays in the the French Enlightenment n.d. (Box 15)
  - Pennybold n.d. (Box 15)
  - Pride and Prejudice 1976 (Box 15)
  - The Quaint and Curious Quest of Johnny Longfoot 1947 (Box 16)
  - The Ring 1964, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - The Ring 1964 (Box S-33)
  - Saroyan's Fables 1941 (Box 16)
  - A Short History of the Printed Word, including photographs and negatives 1970 (Box 16)
  - Sleeping Beauty 1961, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Story of Easter n.d. (Box 17)
  - The Temptation of Saint Anthony 1943 (Box S-32)
  - They Say Stories 1960, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - They Say Stories 1960, 2 folders (Box S-30)
  - Thomas Jefferson Father of Democracy 1953 (Box 17)
  - Tom Jones 1982, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Tom Jones 1982 (Box 18)
  - Twelve Who Dared n.d. (Box 18)
  - Upside-Down World n.d. (Box 18)
  - A Voyage to Laputa 1976, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Wine and the Good Life 1965 (Box 18)
  - Wines of France 1951 (Box 18)
  - "Words in Lines" - Bestiary Sketches n.d. (Box 18)
  - Young Geoffrey Chaucer 1952 (Box 18)
  - Photographic Negatives, chiefly for illustrations in Warren Chappell’s book, A Short History of the Printed Word n.d. (Box 19)